Inventory of the Herman Recht Papers 1943-1946
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Herman Recht Papers 1943-1946
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2001.31
780.00
This collection is comprised of more than 700 letters written by Herman Recht (1908-1971), a Navy yeoman, from Camp Peary (U. S. Naval Construction Training Center), near Williamsburg, Virginia, between October, 1943 to February 1946 to his wife, Esther, in Clairton, Pennsylvania. There are no letters from Esther because, as he wrote to her, saving them would make him homesick.
Herman Recht, 1908-1971 arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 07/04/2001.
Biographical Note
He was born in Lviv Ukraine. Married to Esther who lived in Clairton, Pennsylvania while he was a Navy yeoman at Camp Peary (U. S. Naval Construction Training Center), near Williamsburg, Virginia, between October, 1943 to February 1946. Recht had been a lawyer for eight and a half years before joining the Navy. He was Jewish. Further information about this individual or organization may be available in the Special Collections Research Center Wiki: http://scrc.swem.wm.edu/wiki/index.php/Herman Recht.
Scope and Contents
This collection is comprised of more than 700 letters written by Herman Recht (1908-1971), a Navy yeoman, from Camp Peary (U. S. Naval Construction Training Center), near Williamsburg, Virginia, between October, 1943 to February 1946 to his wife, Esther, in Clairton, Pennsylvania. There are no letters from Esther because, as he wrote to her, saving them would make him homesick.
Recht had been a lawyer for eight and a half years before joining the Navy. He was very well read, and regularly came into Williamsburg to dine at the Williamsburg Lodge and borrow books from and read magazines in the William and Mary library where his interests ran from public affairs to the latest fiction. He often inquires about activities in the Jewish community in Clairton, and is a strong advocate for racial minorities. He is very knowledgeable about classical music. He regularly reads the Pittsburgh Press and inquires about friends and family in Clairton and Pittsburgh. Gossip about friends from home is included in almost every letter.
Arrangement of Materials
Letters are arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
College of William and Mary
Genre/Form of Material:
Correspondence
Occupation:
United States--Lawyers
Topical Term:
African Americans; United States--Jewish History.; United States--Social life and customs.; Williamsburg (Va.)--History.; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Prisoners of War
Detailed Description of the Collection
  Series 1: Folders 1-100: 30 October 1943-30 January 1944
- Folders 1-100: 30 October 1943-30 January 1944
  - (1)
      Subseries 1: Folders 1-10: 30 October 1943-3 November 1943
    - Folders 1-10: 30 October 1943-3 November 1943 (1)
      70,000 people at Camp Peary, 1,400 arrive in one day---all clothes stenciled “H.Recht”—gross pay $50; has worked in journalism, law and family furniture store; knows German, French and Yiddish; Address: Herman Recht, A.S., Plat. 1678, Area C-8, Camp Peary, Va.—75% of fellow sailors are married; HR is “almost 35” years old—barracks mates know that he is a lawyer; refers to request by Marian Anderson that the Daughters of the American Revolution suspend, for her concert, its segregated seating policy { In 1939 the DAR refused to let her sing in Constitution Hall); a military film shown on the base about “Jugoslavs” was not “unadulterated”
      Subseries 2: Folders 11-20: 4 November 1943-15 November 1943
    - Folders 11-20: 4 November 1943-15 November 1943 (1, 2)
      He is the only Jew in the barracks—other men are about age 28-38, mostly technicians. Sailors on 12-hour leave go to Williamsburg since they may not make it back from Richmond on time. Refers to Seabees in Casablanca, Sicily, and Salerno. He will be promoted from Apprentice Seamen (A.S.) to 2d Class Seaman and maybe to 1st Class Seamen at the end of boot camp. Volunteers for yeoman duty when call made for typists—plays chess—men 35 and older exempted from the obstacle course—regularly visits a rabbi. Tells Esther that he doesn’t save her letters because he doesn’t want to make himself homesick.
      Subseries 3: Folders 21-30: 15 November 1943-21 November 1943
    - Folders 21-30: 15 November 1943-21 November 1943 (1, 3)
      On yeoman duty for 8 ½ hours but didn’t have more than 15 minutes work. Isn’t allowed to use typewriter to write personal letters during work hours. Laundry must be hung properly—whites on the whites line and blues and other colored items on the blues line; explosion in Yorktown on the 16th. Men chop wood for fuel. Most men have more to offer the war effort than his “less brawny and less combat or-construction skilled brains have to give.” Jobs are frequently shifted; lawyers doing mosquito control, insurance work, and lecturing. Would like time to read and listen to music; reads L’il Abner comic strip. Peary is the only boot camp for Seabees in the country. Some Chief Petty Officers aren’t too bright. HR is reading ”The Psychology of the Fighting Man.” Unlike sailors, soldiers can send clothes to a laundry. His promotion to S2C is a “big event.”
      Subseries 4: Folders 31-40: 22 November 1943-1 December 1943
    - Folders 31-40: 22 November 1943-1 December 1943 (1, 4)
      Had to shave by razor since electricity is frequently cut off during the day—all 58 pieces of clothing are expected to fit in a white sea bag. Accepted for yeoman training---was sort of interested in storekeeper’s school. He thinks his letters sound dull and asks Esther’s view. An 18 year-old Vermonter with a harsh and shrill voice is uncomfortable with the swearing that goes on. He is “getting apt in the use of “fuckin’” this and “fuckin’” that with all the various nuances.”
      Religious Emphasis Week; heard several talks by Rabbi Philip S. Bernstein, of Rochester, NY relating to Jews in Palestine and Central Europe. A friend at home writes that the new assistant conductor of the New York Philharmonic, “that young Bernstein” is a friend of hers. Convinced of the evils of organized religion and of the “tommyrot of much of the ritual.” No cameras allowed—doubts that he could be admitted to officer training due to his defective eyes. A fellow sailor dislikes the Southerners for their prejudices but “they don’t mind sleeping with black gals.” A record 2,150 inductees in one day.
      Subseries 5: Folders 41-50: 1 December 1943-10 December 1943
    - Folders 41-50: 1 December 1943-10 December 1943 (1, 5)
      Rumor that camp will become a prison camp—Boston Symphony programs sound interesting—no shortage of chocolate bars or Rinso. Hopes to read the Old Prophets, good poetry, and Latin and Greek poets and philosophers. He and friends see Peary as being on a vast WPA or CCC at times. Esther sends food including the coveted bananas, wants her to perfume her next letter with Tabu. Has word that his [furniture?] business is picking up. On 7 December 1943 letter, he writes “2 years after “ [anniversary of Pearl Harbor attack]; hopes he won’t have opportunity to write “3 years after.” The typing and shorthand teacher has a Ph.D. Saw “As Thousands Cheer.” with Lena Horne (”all her gorgeous self”), Mickey Rooney, and Katherine Grayson. Music by Jose Iturbi. Friend had a beer in tavern in colonial building. His wedding anniversary is December 29. Wants to renew his subscription to Free World. H.R> takes the role of an attorney for the accused in mock courts martial. Veterans Administration in Pittsburgh notifies him at home that he is civil service legible and certified as an attorney and announces a vacancy for a Field Examiner Grade CAP-7 at $2,600 per annum.
      Subseries 6: Folders 51-60: 11 December 1943-25 December 1943
    - Folders 51-60: 11 December 1943-25 December 1943 (1, 6)
      Liberties are 21 hours and 62 hours.; 98 on a spelling test. Rumor that 7,000 women office workers in the District of Columbia have moved from private rooming houses to government dormitories. Describes how life insurance is paid in the event of his death. The new Caruso album got rave reviews morning sky was particularly Wedgwoodian in its blue. Will subscribe to the “Nation” and the “New Republic.” Reading “Philosopher’s Holiday” by Irwin Edman.
      Subseries 7: Folders 61-70: 26 December 1943-30 December 1943
    - Folders 61-70: 26 December 1943-30 December 1943 (1, 7)
      Temporarily assigned to make records of long distance phone calls received. Hopes to hear Ezio Pinza on the radio, His 8th wedding anniversary is December 27.—weather continues “stinkeroo.” Looking forward to whenever the war ends and getting back too civilized living. Fathers have a real interest in the war—they ought to take all available non-fathers first— the young have what it takes to fight these stupid wars. Live in and for today while maintaining some perspective as to possible future. Number of Seabees began at 99, rose to 3,000 and are now at 262,000. Service men should be allowed to board trains ahead of all others-they deserve a comfortable ride since they get one so infrequently. Saw “The Lodger” with Merle Oberon, George Sanders and Laird Cregar.—it would frighten children. Post office on the base is heated by wood fires. Pork is now available without ration points. –[Foreshadowing of D-Day]. Has the feeling that any day there may be a gigantic action and the first waves of men pouring into Europe will result in huge casualty lists. Steel strike is pending—labor shouldn’t strike just because no new contract is signed—wait until the new contract omits retroactive provisions. Labor is giving FDR [Franklin D. Roosevelt] one hell of a thank you. Max Werner making predictions for 1944 in Look magazine says that Germany will have a military and political collapse next year.
      Subseries 8: Folders 71-80: 31 December 1943-8 January 1944
    - Folders 71-80: 31 December 1943-8 January 1944 (1, 8)
      Going to a Burton Holmes film and lecture on Mexico City. Morale is low due to new liberty policy with a 60 mile limit. French and Norwegian sailors are atationed at Norfolk. Refers to family “businesses”[a furniture store—Recht’s Furniture, 534 Miller Avenue, Clairton, Pa-- and a grocery store]. Americans are going to be in for terrible shocks soon. Will be hell when invasion gets going. Air bombing won’t prevent the first-wave men from difficulties. Has read what happened at Salerno, Dieffe, and Tarawa. Russian part of war is much worse. Wife recently saw Gilbert and Sullivan’s “Trial by Jury.” Thinking about applying for officers’ training. Listened to Drew Pearson and Walter Winchell on radio. Greyhound may take over the camp bus lines to Richmond and Washington. Much work is divided among many more men than is necessary. A fellow sailor has a Ph.D. in history and is in charge of one of the small libraries in the camp—he knows several languages but no attention is paid to language qualifications. A colored [his word] company is performing La Traviata in Pittsburgh at end of month with tenor Joseph Lipscomb. The train service from Williamsburg to Richmond is not good,. Chocolate bars are available again. Saw “Destination Tokyo” with Cary Grant. Fellow servicemen amazed at his legal background compared to his rating. He was drafted and has to serve for the duration of the war or the national emergency and 6 months thereafter. Went to a concert in Williamsburg; many servicemen and civilian women. William and Mary students served as ushers. Liked the Brahms sonata and the Jamaican Rumba. Tries to write his wife at least one letter a day but is concerned that he can’t write a sensible letter in smooth flowing English. Wife will try to get a reservation at the Williamsburg Lodge. She should mention his rating-Seaman 2d Class. Fellow sailor hopes to buy up oil leases at his next duty station and resell them to private oil companies at a great profit.. Plans to see “Cry Havoc” with Margaret Sullivan at the “local.” Heard Claire Primrose in an opera in Richmond. Has visited Mexico.
      Subseries 9: Folders 81-90: 9 January 1944-17 January 1944
    - Folders 81-90: 9 January 1944-17 January 1944 (1, 9)
      Wants a subscription to Time magazine. Concerned that the general American public doesn’t take the war seriously. Reads the American Magazine—February 1944 issue has the beginning of a novel by Franz Werfel. News story about government program for oil development overseas—Alaska, Burma, India, Persia, and Dutch East Indies are possibilities—private oil interest are opposed. Has never been close to his father—mother is deceased. Unpaved roads have been paved with a hard surface. The Seabees are also in Bougainville in the Solomon Islands. Likes foreign correspondence section of the Christian Science Monitor. Article by Arthur Koestler on war attitudes in the New York Times Magazine. Heard pianist Jose Iturbi in concert. Surprised at the anti-Roosevelt sentiment at the camp. Annoyed that people make their military heros in public administrators and statesmen. Doesn’t like being called by his full first name.
      Subseries 10: Folders 91-100: 17 January 1944-30 January 1944
    - Folders 91-100: 17 January 1944-30 January 1944 (1, 10)
      Got in line for phone sat 1:15 pm (46th in line) and reached the phone at 5:15 pm. Clear and sane article on Roosevelt by Eliot Janeway in December 1943 Fortune magazine. Tries to write daily but often feels at a loss as to what to say. Esther’s father owns a store on Burrows Street [ in Pittsburgh.] Several Jewish Seabees—surprised that many are heavy equipment operators. Interested in working in the camp library. May take a course in conversational Spanish.
  Series 2: Folders 101-200: 31 January 1944-6 June 1944
- Folders 101-200: 31 January 1944-6 June 1944
  - (2)
      Subseries 1: Folders 101-110: 31 January 1944-7 February 1944
    - Folders 101-110: 31 January 1944-7 February 1944 (2, 1)
      Thinks there will be a heightening of United States, British, and Chinese forces against the Japanese. The war will cause terrible scars and the people will continue to be greedy bastards. The cousin of “Louise” teaches music at William and Mary. –Music Department should hold a series of concerts for servicemen. Reading another Irwin Edman book, “Candle in the Dark” and “Yesterday is Dead” by Stuart Cloete. Has the German measles and is in sick bay—first time ever in the hospital. Radio says that journalist, Raymond Clapper has died in a bomber over the Marshall Islands. Has had ice cream every day since he arrived at the camp. Americans may take Rabaul in Papua New Guinea. Much increase in war bond sales since stories of Japanese atrocities became known.. Harold Ickes has announced that U.S. will construct a 1,200 mile pipe line from the Persian Gulf to the eastern Mediterranean. Listening to Mahler’s 4th Symphony played by the New York Philharmonic Orchestra. Food isn’t hot and half the time no salt or sugar. Thinks Germany will surrender with the next six months or so. Wishes that music departments at William and Mary and the University of Richmond would create a joint concert series. Hear a broadcast from Mexico City of Elias Breeskin’s group. New cereal –bran with raisins-amazed that both are in a single box. Heard Herbert Marshall and Monty Wooley singing “Mairzy Dotes.”
      Subseries 2: Folders 111-120: 8 February 1944-16 February 1944
    - Folders 111-120: 8 February 1944-16 February 1944 (2)
      Got his first issue of the New Leader. Thinks it’s anti-communist but socialist. Oil line from the Persian Gulf to Alexandria will help ships in the Mediterranean area and those coming through the Suez Canal into waters near Burma and India. Western terminus may be Haifa. Reading “The Lone Wolf” – has succumbed to mysteries. Has read one by Raymond Chandler. Too late to find a “Will You Be My Valentine?” “Why do I need one?—you is my Valentine you is.” Hopes Esther can again spend 5 or 6 days at the Williamsburg Lodge. Read “The Great Impersonator” Heard from Louise’s cousin who teaches music at William and Mary. Hopes to attend a concert with her; Miss [Natalie Jena] Rosenthal. Fellow Seabee is going to IBM School at the camp. “That’s International Business Machines—big and complex things that punch out the card records.” A few hundred men are in the camp brig. New enlarged library. A “shul”, a synagogue for Orthodox and Chasidiim Jews has been built at the camp—the first for the Navy.
      Subseries 3: Folders 121-130: 16 February 1944-13 March 1944
    - Folders 121-130: 16 February 1944-13 March 1944 (2, 3)
      Helps other servicemen with their income tax forms. Esther receives a $50 monthly allowance from the government. Refers to Victory Tax, a wartime income tax. Got his transcripts in case he applies for a commission. He was 12th in a law class of 69. Finds the service is stressful—asks Esther to withhold some of her remarks about her unhappy lot. Received a letter of recommendation from Dr. [Judson Adams] Crane, Dean of the [University of Pittsburgh] law school. Couldn’t get a room in the Lodge for the Saturday and Sunday of her visit. They will stay in a house on Cary Street, off Jamestown Road; the landlord’s name is Whitacre. Talked to a “negro” from New York about treatment of blacks by whites; New Yorker can’t understand why blacks are not accepted as humans like other people and treated accordingly. He must restrain his temper at times when he would prefer not to and remain quietly satisfied knowing that an ignoramus is that regardless of race or rating. Talked to the Chief Petty Officer in charge of libraries and there may he an opening. Reading “They Shall Not Sleep” by Leland Stowe. Saw Hedy Lamarr in “The Uninvited.”
      Subseries 4: Folders 131-140: 14 March 1944-27 March 1944
    - Folders 131-140: 14 March 1944-27 March 1944 (2, 4)
      Hopes to move from a yeoman unit to a job in the camp library. Wants to find out about the difference in amount of leave between working at the library and in the transportation pool. Got a recommendation letter for his transfer to the library or transportation job from H. Passamaneck, Director of the Young Men’s and Women’s Hebrew Association. Finally gets transferred into the Transportation office. He finished “They Shall Not Sleep” by Leland Stowe, which talks about the future relations between the US and Russia; there is talk about making the camp into regular navy. Has gotten his leave approved, and saw the movie “Lady in the Dark;” supposedly will be getting 3,000 people who can’t read or speak English in camp later this week. Talks about how the postwar period will be something to observe and live through, for many latent prejudices will come out then. Talks about Jewish services at the Camp, and how they are uninspiring; watched the movie “Purple Heart”; bringing more regular navy to the base. Has been put on special assignment, meaning he does not meet the Navy’s physical standards, as the Navy is now integrating SA men into the entire Navy, not just putting them into the Seabees.
      Subseries 5: Folders 141-150: 28 May 1944-5 April 1944
    - Folders 141-150: 28 May 1944-5 April 1944 (2, 5)
      First day in Transportation office, had to move to a new barracks. Goes to the library to read magazines and newspapers; got his liberty schedule. Talks about Fred Woltman, a newspaper writer, and his change in politics; mentions the Dies Committee. Hears rumors that all the Seabee men at the camp will be transferred across the country; is reading Pierre Van Paasen’s “The Forgotten Ally”; calls war a “stupid extravaganza.” Men are starting to get transferred out of Camp Peary by train. Makes comments about a speech of Churchill that was on the radio, and about the White Paper. Peary is being changed to a “general service camp.” Talks about Winchell’s response to Dies. Reads Joe Rosenfarb’s book “Highway to Tokyo.” Comments on and includes an article about the Supreme Court ruling allowing African-Americans to vote in primaries.
      Subseries 6: Folders 151-160: 6 April 1944-13 April 1944
    - Folders 151-160: 6 April 1944-13 April 1944 (2, 6)
      Finds out that he will not be transferred to another base. Talks about the upcoming presidential election. Goes to a Seder meal; talks about rent in Williamsburg, at $8 a week; talks about being a checkers champion. Saw the documentary “Tunisian Victory.” Wants to do some reading on public housing, such as work in community centers. Sees most of the older officers getting transferred out as new recruits are being brought in; there is a shortage of Coca-Cola. Makes plans for his wife Esther to come down and see him. Describes his daily routine, and compares it to his home routine.
      Subseries 7: Folders 161-170: 14 April 1944-12 May 1944
    - Folders 161-170: 14 April 1944-12 May 1944 (2, 7)
      Goes to see the movie “Shine On Harvest Moon;” wonders about the new enlargement of the reserve forces. Finds out that he is a part owner in a furniture business in Clairton, PA; reads an editorial by Henry Wallace, Vice President of the US. Wants to get on community development when he gets home. Takes a walk around the campus of William and Mary; watches a newsreel describing Camp Peary as on beautiful Virginia countryside, which the people watching disagreed with vocally; listens to a concert by Vronsky-Babin piano duo; goes to see the movie “Follow the Boys.” Starts speculating that the invasion will come soon, as British censors are becoming more strict. Describes the sudden transfer order of 15 men from his department. Goes to a doctor to check his eyes and see if they are good enough for him to become an officer. Notes that, had he been assigned to the library instead of the transportation department, he likely would have been transferred to another camp by now; been at Camp Peary for six months. Watches the movie “A Voice in the Wind;” is collecting chewing gum for Esther. Is thankful for the fact that he has access to books and newspapers, as it allows him to keep a semblance of civilian life and prevent moodiness; wants to take a class in conversational Spanish.
      Subseries 8: Folders 171-180: 13 May 1944-20 May 1944
    - Folders 171-180: 13 May 1944-20 May 1944 (2, 8)